Guide to the Samuel Barrington Letterbooks
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Samuel Barrington letterbooks
1778-1779
OSB MSS 85
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.04
(4 boxes)
Two letterbooks of incoming correspondence kept by Admiral Samuel Barrington during his command in the West Indies as Rear Admiral of the White. Correspondents include members of the Admiralty Board; junior officers; Admiral John Byron, who superseded Barrington as commander; officers of the French Navy, including Admirals de Bouillé and d'Estaing; government officials from various West Indian islands, including Valentine Morris of St. Vincent's and William Mathew Burt of St. Christopher; and Lord George Macartney, governor of Jamaica. Subjects include Barrington's secret orders to attack St. Lucia; intelligence on the French fleet and preparations for the battle of Grenada; prisoner exchanges with the French Navy; the defensive requirements of the British West Indies and the fears of the inhabitants; and Barrington's plans to return to Great Britain in July 1779. Other correspondence includes routine messages concerning provisions, shipping, and the welfare of Barrington's sailors.
Barrington, Samuel, 1729-1800
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the William Reese Co. on the James Marshall Osborn Fund, 1997.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Barrington, Samuel, A Journal of the Proceedings....1778-1779: Osborn Shelves fc.147.
SAMUEL BARRINGTON, 1729-1800
Samuel Barrington, the fifth son of John Barrington, first Viscount Barrington, entered the Royal Navy at age 11 under the tutelage of Lord George Gordon and received command of the frigate the Lark in 1747. After a distinguished career during which he captured several French vessels, in January of 1778 Barrington was promoted to Rear Admiral of the White and sent to the West Indies as commander in chief of the fleet there. While Barrington's official command was to guard the British West Indies against the expected arrival of the French fleet under the command of the comte d'Estaing, his secret mission was to take the French island of St. Lucia. He accomplished the capture despite many difficulties, but he lacked the force necessary for an adequate defense of the British West Indies; St. Vincent fell to the French in June of 1779, and Grenada surrendered on July 3.
Barrington's command was superseded on the arrival of Admiral John Byron from North America in early 1779, and he sailed for England shortly after taking part in the inconclusive Battle of Grenada on July 6 of that year. He refused command of the Channel fleet, and remained out of service until April 1782, when he was appointed to the Channel fleet as Lord Howe's second in command. In 1787 he was promoted to Admiral, and served for the last time in 1790, again as Howe's second in command. Admiral Samuel Barrington died in 1800.
Scope and Contents
The Samuel Barrington Letterbooks consist of correspondence and supporting documents received by Barrington during his service as Rear Admiral of the White in the West Indies.
The letterbooks document British naval strategy and policy in the West Indies from the French recognition of the United States in February 1778 through the Battle of Grenada (July 6, 1779). Contents include orders, secret orders and commands received by Barrington from the Royal Admiralty and its offices; communications and intelligence reports from junior officers in the British fleet, and from Admiral John Byron; letters, petitions and memorials by members of the governments of several West Indies islands; and letters from French commanders and an American agent concerning prisoner exchange and prisoner welfare. The letterbooks have been disbound and the letters have been kept in the order in which Barrington arranged them, which was by correspondent or group of correspondents and then chronologically. There are two series: Series I, Letterbook One, and Series II, Letterbook Two. The major topic of each letter is generally indicated in the box and folder listing for that letter.
Series I, Letterbook One, opens with "Admiralty Orders and Letters," consisting largely of letters from the Admiralty and the Admiralty Board. Many are signed by Philip Stevens, Admiralty Secretary; other orders and instructions are signed by the full Admiralty Board, which included the Earl of Sandwich, the Viscount of Lisburne, and others. In addition to the official letter of appointment, located in folder 2, the subseries contains copies of Barrington's secret instructions to take the island of St. Lucia; an extract of a letter from Lord George Germain detailing British hopes for the speedy surrender of Martinique and Guadalupe; copies of petitions from West Indies residents to Germain; and business correspondence regarding provisioning, supplies, prizes, and changes in command.
Letters from Barrington's subordinates are principally concerned with intelligence of d'Estaing's fleet and of other French troop movements in North America. Folders 38-49 contain letters from Admiral John Byron, who replaced Barrington as commander in chief in the West Indies. A letter written January 28, 1779 offers Barrington the option of staying in the West Indies under Byron or returning to England; several folders contain charts of the line of battle and the lists of signals used during the Battle of Grenada on July 6, 1779. The final letter from Byron, written on July 10, directs Barrington to return to England at once to inform the Admiralty of "the true state of these Islands."
Series II, Letterbook Two, opens with letters from General James Grant concerning the logistics of the attack on St. Lucia. These are followed by correspondence concerning prisoner exchange, primarily from the Marquis de Bouillé, although there are two from d'Estaing himself. Folder 61 contains a letter from William Bingham, U.S. agent for the West Indies, proposing a prisoner exchange between the British and American forces; there is no reply noted.
Folders 79-119 hold letters received by Barrington from governors and representatives of various islands, including William Mathew Burt, governor of St. Christopher; Edward Hay, governor of Jamaica; Valentine Morris, governor of St. Vincent's; and George, Lord Macartney, governor of Grenada. Subjects include the repeated demands of the island governments for better defense by the British Navy; reports of skirmishes and attacks and intelligence concerning the French fleet; the collapse of the defenses on Domenica; shipping schedules and provision requests; and prisoner exchanges and prison living conditions. The letters by Morris give his version of the fall of Domenica and his view of the future defense of St. Vincent's. Letters from Edward Hay, Governor of Jamaica, are much concerned with the French prisoners being held at Bridgetown in the wake of a riot and attack on them by some Jamaicans, "white and black."
The letterbook concludes with routine correspondence from the Admiralty's Victualing Office and the Office of Sick and Hurt Seamen.
Anglo-French War, 1778-1783; Anglo-Spanish War, 1779-1783; France -- History, Naval -- 18th century; Great Britain -- History, Naval -- 18th century; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Naval operations; West Indies, British -- History -- 18th century; Barrington, Samuel, 1729-1800; Bingham, William, 1752-1804; Bouillé, François-Claude-Amour, marquis de, 1739-1800; Burt, William Mathew; Byron, John, 1723-1786; Estaing, Charles Henri, comte d', 1729-1794; Gambier, James Gambier, Baron, 1756-1833; Howe, Richard Howe, Earl, 1726-1799; Macartney, George Macartney, Earl, 1737-1806; Morris, Valentine, -1789; Sandwich, John Montagu, Earl of, 1718-1792; Stephens, Philip; Vaughan, Wilmot, Earl of Lisburne, 1728-1800; Great Britain. Admiralty; Great Britain. Royal Navy
- Letterbook One, Series I
  - ADMIRALTY ORDERS AND LETTERS
    - Index of contents, [1779?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Order concerning W. Hickes, gunner of the "Prince of Wales." Signed by Philip Stephens., 1778 Feb 17
    - Order concerning Dr. Hulme's "Medicine for Cure of the Scurvy." Signed by Stephens., 1778 Feb 26
    - Order and letter appointing Barrington Commander in Chief of His Majesty's Ships and Vessels "at Barbadoes, the Leeward Islands, etc." Signed by Sandwich, J. Buller, Lisburne., 1778 Apr 24-25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Orders detailing Barrington's instructions for his mission to the West Indies: copy., 1778 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Order to administer the Supremacy Oaths tests to newly appointed officers. Signed Stephens, Buller, Spencer, Lisburne., 1778 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Secret order to put to sea to Barbados instead of Antigua. Signed Stephens., 1778 May 3
    - Secret instructions to join and assume command of the convoy of Commodore Hotham off Carlisle Bay of Barbados and to proceed to St. Lucia to assist in the taking of the island. Signed Stephens, Sandwich, Buller, Lisburne and Penton: copy, 1778 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Order to convey dispatches from Lord George Germain to island governors, Hay Burt, Macartney and Morris. Signed by Stephens., 1778 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Order to assume command of HMS Boyne and its commander Capt. Sawyer. Signed Stephens, Sandwich, Buller, Lisburne., 1778 May 15
    - Letter to inform Barrington that orders were given Lord Sheldham at Plymouth in regards to Barrington's capture of a schooner bound from North Carolina to France. Signed by Stephens., 1778 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Order to investigate why the Aurora had not gone to Tobago, and to station it or another frigate there. Signed Stephens., 1778 Jun 4
    - "Memorial of the Merchants and Proprietors of the Island of Tobago." Signed by Ferguson, Pulteney, Spottiswoode, Horne, Miller and McQueen., [1778] (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Order to purchase four ships. Signed by Stephens, Spencer, Lisburne, Penton., 1778 Jun 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Letter from Php. Stephens to direct some Ship of War to see the Tortola Trade in safety till they join the Homeward Bound Trade:" copy signed by Stephens, 1777 Feb 5
    - Order to "seize and destroy" all French ships. Signed Stephens, Sandwich, Lisburne, Penton., 1778 Jul 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Order to cooperate with Maj. General Grant in seizing French possessions. Signed by Stephens, Sandwich, Lisburne, Penton: "Secret", 1778 Aug 14
    - "Extract of a secret Letter from Lord George Germain to Major General Grant", 1778 Jul 29
      Scope and Contents
      Concerns hopes for surrender of Martinique and Guadalupe if the inhabitants are promised "the full enjoyment of their possessions and the free exercise of their Religion."
    - Letter establishing Barrington's command over Capt. Robertson and his ship. Signed Stephens, Sandwich, Buller, Palliser., 1778 Feb 21 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Direction to receive Gov. Valentine Morris of St. Vincent, and his family, on board a ship bound for England. Signed Stephens, Sandwich, Lisburne, Penton., 1778 Aug 19 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letter from Stephens informing Barrington that the Comte d'Estaing and the Toulon Squadron anchored off Sandy Hook., 1778 Aug 29
    - London Gazette Extraordinary, 1778 Aug 24
    - Letter from Stephens regarding fleet provisions., 1778 Oct 8 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letter from Stephens regarding reinforcements to West Indies fleet., 1778 Nov 11 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Petition to Lord George Germain from the "proprietors and merchants of the islands of Tobago, Coriacou, and the Grenadines:" copy (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Cover letter by Stephens., 1778 Nov 11
    - Letter from Stephens placing Capt. Cornwallis of the Lion under Barrington's command., 1778 Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Letter from Stephens regarding the contractor for provisions: copy., 1778 Nov 16 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letter from Victualing Office. Signed Hanway, Bates, Korke, Slade., 1778 Nov 9
    - Provisions list from Blackburn: copy., 1778 Sep 30 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letter from Blackburn regarding provisions for the fleet., 1778 Oct 28
    - Letter from Stephens regarding provisions: copy., 1778 Dec 3 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Letter from Stephens, Sandwich, Lisborne regarding French ship movements., 1778 Dec 15
    - Order to send reinforcements to Jamaica by Stephens, et al., 1778 Dec 18
    - Letter from Stephens regarding merchants: copy., 1778 Dec 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Cover letter of a proclamation regarding distribution of booty from Stephens., 1778 Oct 7
    - Order naming ships involved in trade to Barbados, Jamaica and Seaward Islands from Stephens, et al., 1778 Nov 10
    - Order to revive orders of 1764 and 1765 with regards to Spanish vessels by Stephens, et al., 1778 Nov 10 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Copy of a Letter from the Earl of Halifax to the Lords Commissioners of Trade and Plantations:" copy., 1764 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Concerning the Spanish at Jamaica
    - Cover letter for the Minutes regarding Bullion in the colonies of the West Indies. Signed H[enry] S[eymour] Conway: copy., 1765 Nov 16
    - Minutes of the Treasury Board: copy., 1765 Nov 15
    - Letter from Stephens regarding seamen on board private ships: with accompanying printed orders., 1778 Dec 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Printed orders from Lord George Germain., 1778 Nov 18
    - Letter from Stephens regarding ships delivering provisions., 1778 Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Order to assume command of the Lion by Stephens, et al., 1778 Dec 15
    - Letter from Stephens regarding provisions., 1779 Mar 7
    - Letter form Stephens regarding survey of ships., 1779 Mar 2
    - Order to assume command of the Proserpine by Stephens, et al., 1779 Mar 13 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Letter of promotion from Stephens, promoting Barrington to Vice Admiral of the Blue and Commodore Rowley to Rear Admiral of the Blue., 1779 Mar 22
    - Letter from Stephens regarding provisions., 1779 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Order marked "secret" from Stephens regarding the role of North American forces in operations against the French in the West Indies: copy., 1779 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Extract of letter from George Germain ordering withdrawal of forces for the upcoming hurricane season., 1778 Apr 1
    - Letter from Stephens regarding ships with 2 or 3 thousand troops to be sent from Brest to Martinique, 1779 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Order to send homeward fleet from St. Christopher's in October. Signed by Stephens., 1779 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Letter from Stephens instructing Barrington to provide opportunities for West Indies inhabitants to send letters to England., 1779 Apr 8
    - Letter from Stephens regarding Barrington's "Journal of Proceedings.", 1779 Sep 17 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - CORRESPONDENCE FROM JOHN YOUNG AND RICHARD HOWE
    - Letter from Young regarding a short trip to Dominique "to let them know we are not so unprovided....", 1778 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Letter from Young regarding his plan to return to England., 1778 Jul 16
    - Letter from Howe postponing the "appointed Aid" due to the strength of the Toulon Squadron., 1778 Jul 29 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Cover letter from Howe., 1778 Jul 31
    - Letter to Joshua Lockwood at Charleston, South Carolina, from David Lockwood in Barbados, 1778 Mar 15
  - CORRESPONDENCE FROM JAMES GAMBIER AND JOHN HOTHAM
    - Letter from Gambier stating supply ships will be sent to Antigua., 1778 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Letter from Gambier stating the French fleet "have got into" Boston., 1778 Oct 21
    - Letter form Gambier stating that 300 pounds be paid the Commander in Chief of the Army., 1778 Oct 21
    - Letter from the Ardent off New York regarding d'Estaing: duplicate by Gambier., 1778 Nov 14 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Letter from Gambier regarding provisions and d'Estaing's intentions for the West Indies., 1778
    - "A list of rebel frigates...laying in Boston Harbor, 6th Decem[be]r 1778," and "account of provisions remaining" from Gambier. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Letter from Hotham regarding date of his joining Barrington., 1778 Nov 6 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Letter from Gambier to Commodore Hotham concerning attack on St. Lucie: copy., 1778 Oct 24
    - List of "Embarkation" and "Return." Names of ships and regiments from Hotham. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - CORRESPONDENCE FROM JOHN BYRON
    - Letter from John Byron regarding French movements in North America, 1778 Nov 10 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Letter from Byron regarding provisions., 1779 Jan 17
    - Letter from Byron regarding provisions., 1779 Jan 19 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Letter from John Byron assuming command of Barrington and his squadron in a conflict with the French., 1779 Jan 18
    - Letter from John Byron requesting "a moment's conversation", 1779 [Jan?] (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Letter from John Byron., 1779 Jan 25
    - Letter from John Byron regarding d'Estaing and his reinforcements., 1779 Jan 26 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Letter from Byron concerning recruits of the Nova Scotia Regiments, 1779 Jan 27
    - Letter from Byron giving Barrington the option of staying or returning to England owing to the "dispute", 1779 Jan 28
    - Table titled "line of battle" from Byron., 1779 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - List of ships of the Red, White, Blue, and orders regarding their flags., 1779 Feb 22
    - Table titled "line of battle" from Byron., 1779 Feb 22
    - Table titled "line of battle" from Byron., 1779 Feb 24
    - Memo regarding flag signals from Byron., 1779 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Letter from Byron regarding signals and alarms., 1779 Mar 1
    - Chart of ships in Red, White, Blue and Yellow and flag positions from Byron., 1779 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - "Line of Battle" chart from Byron., 1779 Apr 26
    - Letter from Byron., 1779 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Memorandum regarding flags., 1779 May 22
    - Memorandum to be ready to put to sea from Byron., 1779 Jun 13 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - "Line of Battle" chart from Byron., 1779 Jun 14
    - Printed broadsheet with manuscript notes by Byron regarding ship signals., 1779 Jul 2
    - "Signals respecting the Army" and "Embarkation Return" charts. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - "Order of Sailing" from Byron., 1779 Jul 2 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - List of "signals to be observed by flat bottomed boats" from Byron., 1779 Jul 2
    - List of flat bottomed boats., n.d.
    - Letter from Byron requesting Barrington's opinion concerning the strength of the French fleet., 1779 Jul 6 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Letter from Byron mentioning Barrington's wounded arm., 1779 Jul 7
    - Letter from Byron for Barrington directing him to return to England to inform the Admiralty of the "condition of the Squadron" and "the true state of these Islands.", 1779 Jul 10
    - Letter from C. Thompson., 1778 Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Letter from Thompson., 1778 Dec 14
    - Letter from Thompson., 1779 Jan 4
    - Letter from Cumming stating that the governors of Guadalupe and Martinico had declared war against England., 1778 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Letter from Silly concerning encounter with French ship., 1778 Sep 10
- Letterbook Two, Series II
  - CORRESPONDENCE FROM GENERAL JAMES GRANT
    - Index to letters. (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Letter from Grant regarding transport of stores., 1778 Dec 14 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Letter from Grant regarding the French., 1778 Dec 16
    - Letter from Grant concerning recent skirmishes., 1778 Dec 17 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Letter from Grant regarding a French infantry attack., 1778 Dec 18
    - Letter from Grant regarding the French erection of batteries., 1778 Dec 21
    - List of "paroles" from Grant., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Memo (unsigned) from Grant concerning rum and provisions., 1778 Dec 25
    - Letter from Grant regarding artillery., 1778 Dec 26
    - Letter from Grant regarding the French and d'Estaing's movements., 1778 Dec 28
    - List of "paroles.", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Letter from Grant concerning signing of documents., 1779 Jan 1
    - Letter from Grant regarding the French and his unwillingness to use "small detachments" to guard islands., 1779 Jan 3
    - "Head Qua[rte]rs Morne Fortune:" list of paroles, 1779 Jan 5 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Letter from Grant regarding provisions., 1779 Jan 5
    - Letter from Grant regarding his uncertainty about d'Estaing's intentions., 1779 Jan 5
    - Parole list from W[illia]m Browne., 1779 Jan [?] (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Letter from Grant regarding postponement of sending a flag of truce to d'Estaing., 1779 Jan 14
    - Additional letter from Grant., 1779 Jan 16
    - Letter from Grant regarding d'Estaing and the Marquis de Bouillé., 1779 Jan 17
    - Parole list., 1779 Jan [?] (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Letter from Grant regarding de Bouillé and the flag of truce., 1779 Jan 18
    - Letter from Grant regarding transports., 1779 Jan 18
    - Letter from Grant regarding provisions., 1779 Jan 18
    - Letter from Grant., 1779 Jan 26 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Letter from Grant regarding provisions., 1779 Jan 27
    - Letter from Grant regarding Governor William Matthew Burt., 1779 Feb 11
  - CORRESPONDENCE FROM THE UNITED STATES
    - Letter from William Bingham, agent for the U.S. in the West Indies, proposing the exchange of captured seamen., 1779 Jan 9 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - CORRESPONDENCE FROM THE FRENCH
    - Letter from Chevalier Demicoud regarding provisions., 1778 [Dec?] 31 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Letter from Demicoud regarding provisions., 1778 Jan 4 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Letter from Marquis de Bouillé regarding the exchange of prisoners., 1778 Sep 17 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Letter from Comte d'Arbaud regarding the exchange of six English prisoners., 1778 Sep 28/29 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Letter from d'Arbaud regarding the arrival of the Sprightly., 1778 Sep 30 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Letter from the Marquis de Bouillé concerning prisoners., 1778 Sep 29 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Letter from de Bouillé regarding exchange of prisoners., 1778 Oct 9 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Report from Capt. Gelineau: copy., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - List of French naval officers by de Bouillé., n.d.
    - Letter from de Bouillé regarding exchange of prisoners., 1778 Oct 26 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Letter from William Mathew Burt regarding the treatment of French prisoners at St. Christopher, especially Capt. Jallineau [Gelineau]., 1779 Jan 6 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Letter (unsigned) from Burt to de Bouillé regarding Gelineau: copy., n.d.
    - Letter from de Bouillé regarding exchange of prisoners., 1778 Nov 30 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Letter from de Bouillé regarding exchange of prisoners., 1779 Feb 1 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Letter concerning his parole by James Richard Dacres (signed by de Bouillé): copy., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Note on exchanged prisoners signed by d'Estaing., 1779 Jan 27 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - "Return of British Prisoners brought from Martinico.", 1179 Jan 9
    - Letter from d'Estaing regarding Capt. Dacres and others., 1779 Jan 27 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Letter from d'Estaing regarding prisoners., 1779 Feb 18
    - Parole list of British officers from M. de [Gareill?]., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Letter from d'Estaing regarding prisoners., 1779 May 22 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Parole letter concerning John Lodrington., 1779 Mar 22
    - Certificate of the Chevalier de Borda regarding a packet on board the Weazle when it was captured., 1779 Mar 22
  - CORRESPONDENCE FROM ISLAND GOVERNORS
    - Letter from Edward Otto Bayer regarding attack on Dominica and the need of Antigua for defenses., 1778 Sep 9 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Letter by William Stewart to the Governor General of the Leeward Islands concerning the attack on Dominica: copy., 1778 Sep 7